<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A general and true memorial of what has been done in the city and principality of Orange, by the express order of the most Christian king, since the Peace of Nimeguen, in the year 1678 where may be seen not only the breach of treaties, but also the violences and outrages of the souldiers, which have utterly ruined this principality.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42596</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825759</idno>
  <idno type="VID">30146</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240857710</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G488A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213343</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825759</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99825759e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42596)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1793:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A general and true memorial of what has been done in the city and principality of Orange, by the express order of the most Christian king, since the Peace of Nimeguen, in the year 1678 where may be seen not only the breach of treaties, but also the violences and outrages of the souldiers, which have utterly ruined this principality.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Suggested imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:30146:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30146:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A general and true MEMORIAL OF</hi> What has been done in the City and Principality of <hi>Orange,</hi> by the express Order of the Most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian King, since the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> in the Year <hi>1678,</hi> where may be seen not only the Breach of Treaties, but also the Violences and Outrages of the Souldiers, which have utterly ruined this Principality.</head>
            <p>THE House of <hi>Orange</hi> has peaceably enjoyed, during the space of more than six hundred years, an Absolute and Independant Power over the Principality of that Name, and especially for near one Age past, under the Princes of the House of <hi>Nassau,</hi> during the Reigns of the Most, Christian Kings, <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d, <hi>Charles</hi> the 9th, <hi>Henry</hi> the 3d, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, who have often given their Letters Patents, in which they expresly name the Word <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> and all those other Rights that depend on it; which could most easily be made appear, if it were judged necessary.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> that now is, having enjoyed his Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, there fell out a Change in the time of the <hi>Dutch</hi> War, in the year 1673. and, under pretence of Reprizals, this Principality was seized on, but was again restored to him by the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen.</hi> The Consequence has plainly discovered, that the Restitution was not made from any good Will, or honest Intention, since the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this Principality soon after began to be greatly molested, on such weak and frivolous Pretences, as are about to be set forth in this Memorial.</p>
            <p>In the year 1679, under pretence that a Cross, which had been set up by a Private Person (without Order and without Authority) on the Ruines of the Castle, had been beaten down, and that by a Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: This so greatly offended the <hi>French</hi> Intendant of <hi>Provence,</hi> that he sent his Secretary to the City of <hi>Orange,</hi> where by the Order of the Most Christian King, he compelled the Consuls of both Religions (for there was a good understanding preserved between them) to cause this Cross to be again set up and more, to assist at the doing of it, with their Formalities, in a Solemn Procession; and for the Punishment of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30146:2"/>a pretended Crime that was never committed, and of which no Person could be found guilty but a poor Hermit; the Intendant commanded another Cross to be Erected in a Publick place, called the <hi>Cirque,</hi> and obliged as well the <hi>Protestant</hi> as <hi>Catholick</hi> Consuls to see it Guarded, and Protected, under the pain of the high Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure of the King his Master.</p>
            <p>Great Disturbances continued in this Town since the Year 1679, by Reason of such an undertaking as this, and from the Threatnings, which from time to time were to be endured, 'till about two or three Years after, <hi>(viz.)</hi> On the 12th, of <hi>August,</hi> 1682. The same Intendant went to <hi>Orange,</hi> and there Executed two Orders of the Council of the King of <hi>France,</hi> whereof one Prohibited the Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any <hi>French</hi> Student, Professing the Reformed Religion, into the Colledge of the said City, and the other deprived Madam <hi>De Cassan</hi> of the Guardianship and Education of her Children, under pretence that she professed the aforesaid Religion.</p>
            <p>The Demolishing of the Castle having laid open the City on that side, the Inhabitants, by Order of his Highness, attempted to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>close it with a single Wall, to secure themselves from the Robberies which were there continually committed: But they had no sooner set their hands to the work, but the Marquess of <hi>Montanegre,</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant for the King of <hi>France,</hi> of the Province of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> came to <hi>Orange</hi> to oblige them to discontinue that Work, and to cause them to Demolish what they had already Built. To which, when the aforesaid Inhabitants would not submit, he ordered to march thither the 15th. day of <hi>August</hi> 1682. the Regiment of <hi>Dragoons</hi> of <hi>Lalande,</hi> with his Company of Guards, which he Quartered on all the aforesaid Inhabitants at his pleasure, during the space of 48 Hours; in which time, they were not only contented to Plunder, and Rifle the People, but likewise committed such unheard of things, not fit to be expressed in Writing; so that nothing but Cries, and hideous Shrieks could be heard in the Houses and Streets; 'tis true indeed, that after the two Days the City having agreed with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders for 40 Pence a piece for each Head, and their Goods which they had parted with, for the sufficient maintenance of the Souldiers, they behaved themselves with a little more moderation; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the aforesaid Regiment did not consist of more then 450 Men, they were obliged to pay for more than 1400, and this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued till the aforesaid piece of Wall, and all those which enclosed the City, Gates, Towers, and Ravelins, were entirely Demolished by the hands of the aforesaid Inhabitants, who were compelled alone to do that Work, which to them was a greater affliction, than if they had been obliged to hire Strangers for that Service.</p>
            <p>After the raizing of the Walls, which was done in 8 days, by the diligence of the Inhabitants, (which the fear of General Plunder, with which they were threatned, obliged them to hasten) they were besides compelled to present the said Officers with a good Sum of Money, to prevail with them to quit the Town, and to pay more then 2500 Livres for the Table of Monsieur <hi>De Montanegre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, they marched from the Town, and lay the day of their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30146:2"/>departure at <hi>St. Paul Trois Chasteaux,</hi> 4 Leagues from <hi>Orange;</hi> but no sooner had the Inhabitants of that Miserable Town begun to breathe after this rude Shock, but News came the 24th. in the morning, in the same Month, and Year, that the same <hi>Dragoons</hi> were returned upon them; which caused so great a Consternation among them, that they ran about the Streets like Distracted Persons, drawing their Wives and Children after them, endeavouring to save themselves, and escape, by their Flight, those Evils which they feared were ready to fall upon them; but the presence of the Major of the said <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons</hi> did a little appease this disorder; because he assured them, that they returned to stay but a few days, and to facilitate their passage into <hi>Provence:</hi> which was true: yet they continued to Quarter as before at 30 Pence a Head.</p>
            <p>This misery was attended with another, for the mean time, whilst the <hi>Dragoons</hi> ravaged the Town, there was Published an Order of Council of the King of <hi>France,</hi> in all the Neighbourhood of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality, by which all manner of Commerce was forbidden with those of the Principality.</p>
            <p>The 14th. of <hi>March</hi> 1682. The Prince <hi>De Isenguein,</hi> pretending some Imaginary Right, by Order and Permission of the King of <hi>France,</hi> seized on all the Revenues of the said Principality; proceeding so far, that by Executing an Order of <hi>Paris,</hi> of the 21st. of <hi>August,</hi> 1684, he compelled the Farmers of his Highness Revenues, to pay him all the Rents of the said Principality; notwithstanding his Highness had received them before; and 'tis by vertue of this Order that he still enjoys them; it's here to be remarked, that till this time, there is no instance, where the Justice of <hi>France</hi> ever thought it self con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to intermeddle with an Affair of this Nature.</p>
            <p>The 10th. of <hi>December,</hi> 1682. An Officer with Eight Souldiers came to <hi>Orange,</hi> and carried thence several of the Inhabitants to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of <hi>Aix,</hi> pretending they were relapsed, notwithstanding some of them had professed the Reformed Religion from their Infancy; among which miserable Persons there was one Servant Maid, which they seized in the House of Mounsieur the President <hi>Du Lubrieres,</hi> pretending she was a Bastard, and by consequence brought up in the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, according to the Declarations of the King of <hi>France;</hi> the greatest part of these poor Creatures were forced to abjure their Religion, and those that would not, were Condemned to Banishment, and to undergo the <hi>Amande Honerable;</hi> particulary the Sieur <hi>Barte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemy,</hi> Regent of the Colledge.</p>
            <p>Whilst his Highnesses Subjects were thus Tormented, all endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours were used at <hi>Paris</hi> to take from him also his Soveraignty; the King of <hi>France</hi> having obliged the Tutors of the Abbot of <hi>Orleance Longueville</hi> to present a Petition to his Council; setting forth that the Principality of <hi>Orange</hi> was adjudged to him, by vertue of a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded gradual Substitution, set down in the Will of the Lady <hi>Mary De Beaux</hi> Princess of <hi>Orange,</hi> in the year 1416. By virtue of the Decree upon that Petition of the 14th of <hi>November</hi> 1682. his Highness was Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to appear by his Officers, and the Officers summoned the Prince by this Title, Messier <hi>William</hi> Count of <hi>Nassau.</hi> The King of <hi>France</hi>'s
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30146:3"/>Advocate at <hi>Paris,</hi> Summoned him in these Words, <hi>Messier</hi> William <hi>of</hi> Nassau <hi>Living at</hi> Amsterdam <hi>in</hi> Holland.</p>
            <p>Mounsieur <hi>Heinsius,</hi> Envoy from the States-General to the Court of <hi>France,</hi> (upon theocccasiou of this Citation and the demolishing of the Walls) obtained at present a stop to these Proceedings; and he had no sooner left the Court, but they began afresh to disquiet His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness Subjects; for on the 8th of <hi>April,</hi> 1684, was published the Edict against the Relapsed, which gave no small disturbance to those of the Reformed Religion, of which some deserted the Town.</p>
            <p>On the 15th of <hi>August,</hi> 1685, Mounsieur <hi>Jacob de Drevon</hi> was il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legally taken out of his House with extream Violence, under pretence of Debt, and carried to the Prison of <hi>Lions;</hi> and tho' the States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> have earnestly pressed the Court of <hi>France,</hi> by their Ministers, for his Liberty, yet could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver obtain it; Mounsieur <hi>Colbert de Croissy</hi> saying always, <hi>That the Orders of the King, his Master, were to be executed in all places:</hi> And so far were they from doing Justice, as was demanded, that as a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Violence, they carried away Mounsieur <hi>Pascall</hi> from <hi>Orange,</hi> falsely accusing him to have deserted his Colours, and having brought him to the Cittadel of St. <hi>Esprit,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> against the Law of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they there shot him to Death.</p>
            <p>It is certain that every Soveraign Lord, or Head Patron, has a right to the Tithes, and other Dues from the Estates of Ecclesiasticks, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Cannons and Custome; so that on this Foundation, as well as many weighty Reasons which cannot be remembred without Horrour, Prince <hi>William,</hi> of Glorious memory, did impose upon all the Ecclesiasticks of his Principality the Sum of 2400 Livers, which he allotted for the maintenance of the Colledge, and other pious uses, at the instance even of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 2 <hi>d,</hi> as appears by his Letters of 28 <hi>February,</hi> and the 1st of <hi>March,</hi> 1553. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Parliament of <hi>Orange,</hi> the only Competent Judge in this Affair, issued out an Order of the 3 <hi>d</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1683, (occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Refusal which the Ecclesiasticks made to continue the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the said sum) which obliged them to continue the payment of it; they were so rash and bold to address themselves to the King of <hi>France,</hi> and by a false Representation, they obtained an Order of Council, of the 14th of <hi>March,</hi> 1684, which not only vacated and nulled what his Highness and Established with so much Justice, but enjoined likewise the Collector to restore such Sums as he had before gathered; which Order was executed with great Diligence, as well as Rigour.</p>
            <p>Although all that has hitherto been said, sufficiently discovers the Design which was formed for the entire ruine of this miserable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality; yet it was not believed it would come so far, as to force the Consciences of his Highness Subjects of the Reformed Religion, and so much the rather, because when those of <hi>France</hi> had suffered the greatest violence, the Count <hi>de Grignan</hi> came to <hi>Orange,</hi> by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the King of <hi>France</hi> (attended only with 50 Dragoons or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers for his Guard) where he assured those of the said Religion, that there should not be the least Violation of their Privileges, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30146:3"/>they received none of the Subjects of the King, his Master, into their Assemblies; but the Consequence has sufficiently made it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that this was only a Lure to lay them asleep; for two days after, at one a Clock in the Morning, the City of <hi>Orange</hi> was inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted with Dragoons, which, setting Guards at all the Avenues, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the Inhabitants from going out: They continued in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, till they searched, and ransacked all the Houses, supposing to find there a great number of the Subjects of the King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Count <hi>De Tesse,</hi> their Commander, being retired to the Bishops Palace, ordered in the interval all the Ministers of the Principality to be called to him, pretending he had somewhat to communicate to them for the good of those of the Reformed Religion; but they were no sooner come together, but he sent them all to the Prisons, having first threatned them with Whipping. The indisposition of Monsieur <hi>Chambrun,</hi> one of the aforesaid Ministers, preserved him from the Prison, 'twas thought enough to confine him, under a Guard, to his own House.</p>
            <p>After this, all the Regiment entred the City, and was Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered there; that is to say, on those of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion was Quartered one third, and on those of the Reformed the other two, and the Community obliged to pay every day 30 pence a Head.</p>
            <p>Two days after the Regiment of Foot of <hi>Dú Plessis Bellieure</hi> arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved also in the Town, where they were in the like manner quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd, and at that time a Detachment of 4 Companys of <hi>Dragoons,</hi> was sent to <hi>Counteson,</hi> a little Town of the Principality. The day after the arrival of the said Infantry, they began to demolish the Temple, but because they found in the Chest neither Money nor Papers, the said Monsieur <hi>de Tesse</hi> caused Madam <hi>de Chion,</hi> wife to one of the aforesaid Ministers, to be imprisoned, that was accused of having taken away all things of that kind, that were in the great Temple. 'Tis true, that for 18 days these <hi>Missionaries</hi> did not directly force any of the Inhabitants to change their Religion; but as soon as there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that began in the least to yield, they discharged them of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the <hi>Dragoons,</hi> which was the Cause that some of the meaner sort abjured their Religion, to ease themselves of such troublesome Guests. The 19th. day the Masque was taken off, and having first environed the City, to hinder the Inhabitants from going out, they declared that the King of <hi>France</hi>'s pleasure was, that they should all go to <hi>Mass;</hi> and in Case they should not voluntarily do it, they had order to compel them.</p>
            <p>The Example of their Neighbours made the greatest part resolve to call an Assembly, wherein they drew up some Articles of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, signed by the Count of <hi>Tesse,</hi> and the Bishop of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> tho' but ill observed on their part; after which, most of those of the Reformed Religion abjured; those that would not abandon their Religion, were treated with the utmost Rigour. Monsieur <hi>de Chambrun</hi> was one of those that suffered most on this Occasion, and tho' he was confined to his Bed, as well by his Ordinary Indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, as by the breaking of one of his Thighs, there was sent to him 45 <hi>Dragoons,</hi> and 8 Drummers, which ceased not for the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30146:4"/>space of 48 hours, to beat their Drums at his Beds head, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from sleeping, which caused him to faint away, but he came again to himself by the Violence of his Pain; neither his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, nor Domesticks were permitted to come into his Chamber, nor any more sustenance allowed him, than was barely necessary to keep him alive. There were many of the Reformed Religion, that on this occasion, offered their Estates to have the liberty of retiring, and others presented themselves to be put to Death, to avoid the temptation of changeing their Religion, but neither was this allowed them. All these miserable Persons having thus yielded to such Cruelty, the Infantry retreated, after a stay of 21 days in the Town, and a little after the <hi>Dragoons</hi> who had stayed thirty; they took with them four Ministers of the Principality, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Goudran, Annet, Chion,</hi> and <hi>Petit,</hi> and put them in Prisons in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoprick of <hi>Valence,</hi> and 8 Months after removed them to <hi>Pierre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encise</hi> in <hi>Lyons,</hi> where they are still kept under close Confinement. Monsieur <hi>Chambrun</hi> was sent banished to the Port St. <hi>Esprit,</hi> from thence to <hi>Valence,</hi> and after into the Mountains of <hi>Danphine,</hi> neer to <hi>Die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilst the Ministers were at <hi>Valence,</hi> Madam <hi>de Chamard,</hi> a young Widdow of a very delicate Complexion, and Temper, went thither to see Monsieur <hi>de Chion</hi> her Brother-in-Law, but no sooner was she come into the Town, but she was seized by the Guards, who having searched her, and finding Psalms about her, carried her to the Hospital General, at her entry the Goaler received her with a Kick on the Belly, and the Servant Maid struck her on the head with the Keys of the said Hospital, which she had in her hand. This Rude treatment having forced from her some Complaints, the said Goaler caused her to be stripped almost quite naked, bound her hands and feet, and gave her a 100 stroaks with a Cord before and behind, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which she was thrust into a deep Dungeon, where she lived three days on Bread and Water, and from whence she had not been so soon released, if the Torments, or the Thirst which she had suffered had not cast her into Distraction: The Physitians in the Town in vain endeavoured to restore her to her right Mind, which was so greatly disordered, that they were constrained to send her back again to <hi>Orange.</hi> Some time after, the Count of <hi>Tesse</hi> returned to <hi>Orange,</hi> to consummate his Mission, and to oblige those that had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned the Reformed Religion, to perform all things which the New Religion they had embraced required of them; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he ordered his Company of <hi>Dragoons</hi> to march thither, where they remained eight Months on the new Converts.</p>
            <p>The 5th. of <hi>April</hi> 1686. <hi>Mounsieur De Lubrieres,</hi> President of the Parliament of <hi>Orange,</hi> was taken away by the Guards of the Count <hi>De Grignan,</hi> and carried to <hi>Pierreencise,</hi> where he still remains. The Cause of his Imprisonment being altogether unknown.</p>
            <p>'Twas about this time, that the Bishop of <hi>Orange,</hi> by Order of the King of <hi>France,</hi> united the Revenues of the <hi>Consistory</hi> to those of the <hi>Hostel-Dieu,</hi> compelled those that were accountable to bring in their Accompts to him; He put out the Directors or Governours of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30146:4"/>
               <hi>Hostel-Dieu,</hi> against the Privileges of the State; by which the four Consuls, when they lay down that Charge, are to take upon them the Care; took away the Cognizance of it from the Council of State, and substituted six Directors in their Places.</p>
            <p>A little time after the Count <hi>De Grignan</hi> sent to <hi>Orange</hi> Monsieur <hi>Janet,</hi> in quality of his Subdelegate, to whom the Community was obliged by the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Order to pay half a Pistol a day, during 9 Months that the stayed there. In that time, he caused a Woman to be cast into the Common-shoar, because she dyed without being Confessed, and Receiving the Communion: banished several Persons of the said <hi>Orange,</hi> and <hi>Courteson,</hi> without any Cause: Among which were two Gentlemen: Shut up several Women in the Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, amongst others. Madam <hi>De Berquarole</hi> with two of her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, where they are still kept; and many of His Highnesses Subjects have been illegally Imprisoned within this year past, under divers pretences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> the 12th. 1686. by Order of the King of <hi>France,</hi> the Farmers of his Highness were forbidden to part with the Money due for their Farm, under pain of Disobedience, till it should be otherwise ordered; which is the reason that the <hi>demesnes</hi> are ruined for want of Repair, that Prisoners remain without subsistance, that Crimes continue unpunished, and that the Officers and Regents of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge are without Sallary, for want of a Publick Treasure.</p>
            <p>The 25th of the said Month and Year, the Council and State of <hi>Orange</hi> being Assembled to proceed according to Custome to the nomination of the Consuls, an Order of the King of <hi>France</hi>'s was brought to them, by which they were enjoyned to Name Monsieur <hi>De Rocheblane,</hi> and <hi>Bransset,</hi> for first and second Consuls, and one <hi>Vieux</hi> for their Secretary, in the room of <hi>Mons. Felix</hi> whom his Highness had established there.</p>
            <p>His Highness having provided according to the usual Custome for the Place of <hi>Viquier,</hi> or Chief Magistrate, and for the Judicature, two Persons, <hi>Mr. Cartes</hi> and <hi>Boyer,</hi> to enter on those Offices the 15th. of <hi>August,</hi> 1686. the Count <hi>De Grignan</hi> some days before sent an Order of the <hi>French</hi> King, to the Council of State, by which he commanded them to continue Mr. <hi>Tibaud</hi> and <hi>Joncq</hi> in the said Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which was accordingly done; though it was represented, that according to the Privileges inviolably observed, they could not be continued.</p>
            <p>The 15th of <hi>August,</hi> the same Year, the Bishop of <hi>Orange, Joncq</hi> the ordinary Judge, an under Delegate of the Intendant of <hi>Provence,</hi> the Quarter Master to the said Count <hi>De Grignan,</hi> two of the said Guards, the Secretary of the said Bishop, and the Register of the said Judge, entred into the House of Monsieur <hi>Sausin,</hi> his Highnesses Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the Rolls, whom the said Judge acquainted with an Order of the said Intendant, importing, that the Place wherein his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness's Rolls were kept, should be opened for the said Bishop, that he might take Copies of such Deeds as would be necessary for him, and in Case that this were not done, to command the Doors to be broke open. To which the said <hi>Sausin</hi> answered, that he must have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30146:5"/>some time to Communicate it to his Highness, and to confer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the matter with his Officers. But the said Judge being unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hearken to any Reason, caused the Door to be broke open by a Smith, and they visited the said Place where his Highness's Rolls were kept, at their Pleasure. Monsieur <hi>de Caderousse,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting the Respect that he owed to his Highness, whose Vassel he is, and being willing to make use of the sad Circumstances, in which this unhappy State was involved, and that he might make his advantage of its Misery, thought good to beg of the <hi>French</hi> King, the Toll of the <hi>Rosne,</hi> under pretence that it had been got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from his Predecessors by Usurpation, tho' he had not the least appearance of Right to it; the august House of <hi>Orange</hi> having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed it for above these six Ages without interruption. This Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition was remitted to the Intendant of <hi>Provence,</hi> who decreed on the 7th. of <hi>September</hi> 1686. that the Petition of the said <hi>Monsieur Caderousse,</hi> should be Communicated to his Highness's Agent, that in 15 days time they might make such Defence as they should think good, which was intimated to them. So short a delay doth plainly shew, that they designed to deprive his Highness of the means of making his Defence. Seeing 'tis impossible the Officers should be able to give him an account of it in so short a time, and recover those Deeds that are necessary, which are in <hi>Holland,</hi> about 300 Leagues from <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The desire also which there is in them to multiply Processes, is observable in this their Conduct, seeing the Officers of his Highness (on a like Quarrel made by the Merchants of <hi>Languedoc</hi> and <hi>Lyon</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the said Toll) have already produced since the Year 1685, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Intendants of the said Province, and of <hi>Dauphine,</hi> the Titles relating to it. 'Tis remarkable, that while the Princes of <hi>Orange</hi> enjoyed the said Toll as a Right independant on any, which was for near Five Ages, no Man thought good to molest them; but since of their own accord, without being compelled to it, they have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged themselves to pay hommage for it to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> which was done in this last Age, they have been continually troubled with Processes, and vexatious Suits.</p>
            <p>It was very near the same time, that the said <hi>Jenet</hi> received a <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niatis</hi> from the Court of <hi>France,</hi> for executing his Commission with too much gentleness toward the new <hi>Romanists,</hi> and with too much Severity against the Jews. The Marshal of the Guards to the Count <hi>De Grignan</hi> was put in his place, to whom they gave 8 or 10 of the said Guards, who were Quartered only in the Houses of those who who were accused for a neglect of their Duty in the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion; where they caused themselves to be entertained profusely, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciously, and from whence the said Marshal extracted a Pistol a day for himself, and a Crown for each of his Souldiers.</p>
            <p>Besides this expensive Entertainment, these miserable persons were all fined; till Mr. <hi>James Duire,</hi> being disabled in his Legs, besides the Quartering the aforesaid persons, was Fined 50 Crowns; many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were treated in the like manner.</p>
            <p>These Guards were relieved by two Companies of <hi>Dragoons</hi> of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30146:5"/>the King's Regiment, that arrived at <hi>Orange</hi> the 21st of <hi>November,</hi> 1686. under a Pretence that some of the Rabble had assembled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in the Night without the Town, and had there Sung Psalms.</p>
            <p>They were all Quartered on the New <hi>Romanists</hi> by the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Order, tho they had discharged the Duties of that Religion, and none of them were at that pretended Assembly. The first brunt of this Quartering fell on the poorest Families, who having neither Money nor Goods, were almost all Imprisoned; so that at present, there is not above 150 that do maintain them, the rest being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the utmost misery, or have forsaken the Town. 'Tis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted that it cost them 5000 Livres a Month; for they do exact for as many more as they really have in their Companies.</p>
            <p>The 6th of <hi>December</hi> following, the new Missionary seized on all the Avenues of the Town, a little before day, and then caused an Order of the King of <hi>France</hi> to be Published, whereby all the Inhabitants were commanded to carry all their Arms to the <hi>Town-House,</hi> on pain of the utmost Rigour, if any did otherwise. The same thing was done in all the other places of the Principality: all these Arms, as well as those of the said <hi>Town-House,</hi> Powder, Bullets, and Match, were carried away into <hi>Provence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 12th. of <hi>November</hi> 1686. Monsieur <hi>Joncq,</hi> Judge of the Town of <hi>Pertuys</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> Subdeligate to the Intendant of the said Province, coming to <hi>Orange,</hi> with the Secretary of the said Intendant, and a certain Souldier of the King's Guards went to his Highnesses Mint, where, in prosecution of a Order of the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Council, of the 30th. of <hi>October</hi> the same Year, he caused an account to be taken of all the Coyns, Stamps, Graving-Irons, Weights, and other Tools and Instruments of the said Mint; Sealed them up, and carried away the Keys at the same time; at <hi>Marseilles</hi> they seized upon <hi>Monsieur Barbier</hi> Master of the said Mint.</p>
            <p>As the Princes of <hi>Orange</hi> were always acknowledged to be the only Founders, Benefactors, and supream Patrons, of the Bishopricks, Churches, and Abbies of the Principality, so that no Man ever had the least appearance of right thereto, as is very plain, even by the Procedure of the Kings of <hi>France.</hi> Who were so far from pretending to a power to Nominate the Bishops, that they have always used intreaties and recommendations, when they have had a mind to have one of their own Creatures placed there, to prevail with the said Princes to present him to the Popes. It's also evident that the said Bishops, before they could take Possession of the said Bishoprick, were fain to go to <hi>Holland</hi> to do hommage, and take an Oath of Allegiance to their Highnesses; yet so 'tis, that since the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> hath caused his Council to make several Orders, whereby Arch-Deaconries, Chapters, Canonships, and Prebendaries of the Cathederal Church of <hi>Orange</hi> are filled up; tho the <hi>Regale</hi> was confirmed by the means of the Oath of Allegiance which the Bishop had taken to his Highness, as his Soveraign and Founder, with the consent of the King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's also fallen out, that tho Madam <hi>Gaspard De Moretan De Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brillan,</hi> whom Prince <hi>Frederick Henry,</hi> of Glorious Memory, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30146:6"/>to the Abbey of St. <hi>Andrew De Ramieres,</hi> in the Year 1641, and made Madam <hi>de Cassan</hi> her Coadjutrix, in the Year 1659. in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Delibertations of the Nuns, which they did peaceably possess; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless, the King of <hi>France</hi> without having any regard thereto, by an Order of his Council of the 8th of <hi>March</hi> 1681, preferred to the said Abbey Madam <hi>Ann De Trissan</hi> of <hi>Veirgne,</hi> Abbess of <hi>Asyle,</hi> tho she professed contrary Rules, and which are inconsistent with those of the Nuns of St. <hi>Andrew.</hi> These proceedings having forced some Complaints from those Religious Women, the King of <hi>France</hi> sent the Intendant of <hi>Provence</hi> to the said St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> who by His Orders took away all the Papers, Deeds, and Charters that were found there, and a little while after the said Madam <hi>De Cassan</hi> Coad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutrix, (and who had the Reversion of the said Abbey, in case she Survived, granted to her by his Highness) was banished to that of <hi>Asyle</hi> in <hi>Languedoc.</hi> The said Madam <hi>De Moretan</hi> being deceased, Madam <hi>Tressan</hi> was put into possession of the said Abbey, where there are not above three or four Nuns left, the others being withdrawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other places.</p>
            <p>This new Abbess was no sooner in possession of the said Abbey, but she desired of the King of <hi>France</hi> a Commission from his Council for all her matters, which was granted her, and whereby the Officers of his Highness are forbidden to take Cognisance of affairs relating unto her; upon this Commission she summoned the Farmer of the Publick Oven of <hi>Jonquieres</hi> belonging to his Highness, and caused a prohibition to be given forth of taking for the future any Wood out of the Forrest of the said St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> for the heating the said Oven. She also caused a prohibition to be given to those who six year ago had bought the Liberty of felling the Wood of <hi>Aumenge,</hi> to continue it, tho the said Wood hath belonged to his Highness time out of mind, and summoned them to make restitution for what they had already paid; having no other right to do so, but that of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, and convenience, which makes her undertake any thing in such a time as this is.</p>
            <p>By an Order of the Council of the King of <hi>France,</hi> of the 6th. of <hi>November</hi> 1686. the Parliament of <hi>Orange</hi> was interdicted, in execution whereof, the Intendant of <hi>Provence</hi> came into the Town, and Communicated the said Order of the 21st. of <hi>December,</hi> the said year, to the Officers of his Highness, forbad them for the future to do any Offices of their places, notwithstanding the Protestation they made, and the Proof they were ready immediately to give, how the things related in the said Order were contrary to Truth. The 28th. of the said Month and Year, the said Intendant gave a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission to <hi>Joncq</hi> the ordinary Judge, his Register, and two other skilful men, to take cognizance of the Repairs that were to be made in the <hi>Demesnes</hi> of his Highness, after they had forbad those that had the care of this Affair.</p>
            <p>He also gave Commissions to the said Judge, to draw up and finish the Process against those that should proceed, contrary to the Edicts of the King of <hi>France,</hi> as well as against those that were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused of having been at the Assembly before mentioned.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30146:6"/>
            <p> At the same time he gave to one St. <hi>Maurin,</hi> the Title of the Kings Attorney for all sorts of Affairs, and ordered to proceed to Sentence against, and seize all the goods of those that had absented themselves since the Persecution, and some time before.</p>
            <p>The 29th. day after the said Intendant came to his Highnesses Mint, where he broken open the Seals which had been put upon it, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed all the Doors and all the Chests to be opened, and after he had viewed and examined the whole, he caused them to be sealed up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresh, and carried away the Keys, together with the Journal of the Officers of the said Mint. The said Intendant withdrawing the aforesaid day, the Judge St. <hi>Maurin,</hi> and <hi>Vieux</hi> began to proceed to the Sentence, and make an Inventory of the Goods of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Gabriel Convenent,</hi> Counsellor of the said Parliament, <hi>John de Granetier,</hi> St. <hi>Colombe, Lewis Berset, Charles Bainty, Peter Bonneau, Paul Deny, John Dedier, Lanis Baillere, Ouger Louis Bourguet,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Julien,</hi> (whose Husband is a Prisoner at <hi>Bruget</hi> near <hi>Lyons,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing seized as he was withdrawing into <hi>Holland,</hi> that he might be readmitted into the service of his Highness) the two Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels her Sisters, and Madam <hi>de Chion,</hi> Wife of one of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters a Prisoner at <hi>Pierrencise,</hi> and many others. The goods of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Chambrun,</hi> of his Wife, and of <hi>John Covenent</hi> his Nephew, being seized on the 18th. of <hi>October</hi> the same year; on which day Monsieur, the said Quarter-master, the said Judge, his Register, and a double Guard, was set on the House of Monsieur <hi>Andrew Convenent</hi> Brother-in-Law (and Attorney) of Monsieur <hi>de Chambrun,</hi> to make an Inventory of his Papers, Books, and Effects. One cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Charles le Croix</hi> (not able to pay his Debts) was named as Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questrator, and Commissioner for all the Goods of the above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, he having already received the Goods of Monsieur de <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, to manifest that the King of <hi>France</hi> would be absolute Master of the City and Principality of <hi>Orange,</hi> against all Right and Justice, The said Intendant caused there to be published all those Edicts, and Declarations, which was never thought fit to be done, even during the <hi>Inter Regnums.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>